Guide to the Michael Meredith Hare Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Michael Meredith Hare papers
1935-1968
MS 6
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, notes, diaries, research materials, and other papers of Michael Meredith Hare, architect, philosopher, and author. The papers relate primarily to Hare's interest in the philosophical, theological, and mystical implications of the creative process and to his attempts to reconcile the laws of physics and parapsychological phenomena. In connection with this work, Hare corresponded with a number of psychologists, mathematicians, physicists, and philosophers. Correspondents of note include Henry Margenau, Percival W. Martin, J. B. Rhine, W. Grey Walter, and Paul Weiss.
Hare, Michael M. (Michael Meredith), 1909-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Michael Hare, 1969.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings, Diary, Notes, and Research Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Studied architecture at Yale University, Columbia University, and Paris, beginning in 1931; in 1954 appointed to design U.S. embassy in Honduras; while in Honduras began the study of philosophy, psychology, and psychical phenomena; wrote several books on these subjects, 1966 and 1968.
Biographical / Historical
Michael Meredith Hare was born on January 17, 1909 in New York city. He was educated at Groton and entered Yale with the class of 1931. In his senior year Hare transferred to the department of architecture. He spent two years in Paris studying architecture, but was dropped by Yale a month after his return and finally took his degree in architecture at Columbia. Hare subsequently practised as an architect, frequently producing controversial designs. In 1931 he married Jane P. Jopling; they had three children. During the Second World War Hare served in the U.S. Marine Corps. In 1954 he was appointed by the President's Commission to design the U.S. Embassy buildings in Honduras.
At about this time Hare was beginning to feel dissatisfied with the restrictions placed upon his architectural ideas by modern economic conditions. He also became more interested in the philosophical and theological implications of the creative process. He was influenced by a book by Percival W. Martin,Experiment in Depth, and began to write a diary of his dreams and mystical experiences, which he kept until shortly before his death. In 1956, while in Honduras, Hare had a series of mystical experiences. As a result of these ideas and experiences, Hare turned to a study of religion, psychology, philosophy and psychical phenomena. He wanted to develop a theory to demonstrate the unity of the universe, which would involve reconciling the laws of physics and para-psychological phenomena. He therefore added mathematics, astronomy, physics and other scientific subjects to his field of study. Hare corresponded with persons involved in all these subjects, asking for their criticism of his theories, or trying to convince them of his ideas. In 1966 Hare published his first book on the problem:Microcosm and Macrocosm: An Approach to the Synthesis Of The Real. In 1968 a second book,The Multiple Universe: On the Nature of Spiritual Reality, was published. Hare was apparently intending to publish a third book, but he died in September 1968, before its completion.
The Michael Meredith Hare Papers are divided into two series: "Correspondence" and "Writings, Diary, Notes and Research Materials." "Correspondence" contains letters received by Hare and his own drafts and copies of replies. Most of the correspondence discusses various aspects of Hare's search for a quantum theory of the solar system, his efforts to reconcile extra-sensory phenomena with nuclear physics, and his interest in symbolism and mysticism. Many of Hare's letters include lengthy expositions of his theories; he frequently sent duplicate copies of these to other persons. Correspondents of note include: Henry Margenau, Percival W. Martin, J.B. Rhine, W. Grey Walter, and Paul Weiss. Hare also wrote to C.S. Jung, and although there are no letters from Jung in the collection, there is in Series II a copy of an article by Hare, "The Compulsion to Symbolize" (1956), which is apparently annotated by Jung.
Series II contains addresses, articles and books by Hare; the dream diary, which covers the period from February, 1956 to August, 1968; and notes and research materials related to Hare's search for a universal law. Notes and research materials, which Hare indicated were directly related to his two books, have been filed after the book manuscript; other notes and research materials are filed separately. There are a large number of notes in the series, most of which involve mathematical calculations. There is some other research material, mainly in the form of printed copies of articles on various scientific topics. There is also one manuscript written by Hare's brother, Montgomery Hare.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, notes, diaries, research materials, and other papers of Michael Meredith Hare, architect, philosopher, and author. The papers relate primarily to Hare's interest in the philosophical, theological, and mystical implications of the creative process and to his attempts to reconcile the laws of physics and parapsychological phenomena. In connection with this work, Hare corresponded with a number of psychologists, mathematicians, physicists, and philosophers. Correspondents of note include Henry Margenau, Percival W. Martin, J. B. Rhine, W. Grey Walter, and Paul Weiss.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Architecture; Mysticism; Parapsychology; Philosophy; Psychology; Diaries; Architects; Bingham, Hiram, 1875-1956; Delgado, José Manuel Rodríguez, 1915-2011; Fitch, Frederic B. (Frederic Brenton), 1908-1987; Hare, Michael M. (Michael Meredith), 1909-1968; Howe, Quincy, 1900-1977; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961; Margenau, Henry, 1901-1997; Maritain, Jacques, 1882-1973; Martin, P. W. (Percival William), 1893-1972; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Rhine, J. B. (Joseph Banks), 1895-1980; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965; Toynbee, Arnold, 1889-1975; Walter, William Grey, 1910-; Weiss, Paul, 1901-2002
- Correspondence, 1956-1967, undated; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the person or organization with whom Hare corresponded. Correspondence with any one individual is arranged chronologically. One folder containing Hare's instructions to his executors is filed at the end of the series.
  - American Geophysical Union(1), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Institute of Physics(1), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Society for Psychical Research(13), 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Analytical Psychology Club of New York(1), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, 1956, 1960, 1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bingham, Hiram (1), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blackett, Patrick Maynard Stuart (1), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campbell, Joseph (3), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cohen, Bob (2), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Crane, Mrs. Sara P. ("Sally"-daughter)(7), [1962-1963?], 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - (to) Dale, Laura (1), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Delgado, José M.R. (2), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dodge, Marshall (1), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica Library Research Service (14) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ferriere, Louis E.(5), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fitch, Frederic B. (5), 1957, 1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Forwald, H. (10), 1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - (to) Fromm, Erich (1), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fry, T.M. (2), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - (to) Ghiselin, Brewster (1), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Goldstein, Richard (2), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Goodwin, Philip (2), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Halverson, Rev. Marvin P. (3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hare, Montgomery (brother)(12), 1956, 1960, 1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hare, Peter (son) (3), 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - (to) [Hare, William?] (uncle) (1), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Haskell, Douglas (editor "Architectural Forum") (4), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - (to) Heisenberg, Werner (2), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Howe, Quincy (with enclosed letter from McVittie, George) (3), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - (to) Hoyt, Rosalie (2), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hudnut, Joseph (4), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - (to) Huntington, Christopher (1), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - (to) Huntington, Katrina, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jenkins, R.V.(1), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jones, Hardin B. (3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Julian Press Inc.?] (2), 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jung, C.[illegible] (replies from Jung's secretary only), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Kretzmann, O.P. (6), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - L, 1956, 1959, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lunt, Storer (5), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - M, 1956-1957, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Montgomery, Ruth (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - McVittie, G.C. (3), 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Margenau, Henry (14), 1957, 1959, 1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Maritain, Jacques (2), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Martin, Percival W. (18), 1956-1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - (to) Moore, Roy (1), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mumford, Lewis (2), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - (to) N.A.S.A. (1), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Northrop, Filmer S.C. (1), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - (to) Osis, Karlis (1), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - P, 1956-1957, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pauli, Wolfgang (1), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - (to) Progoff, Ira (2), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Raz, B. James (1), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rhine, J.B. (9), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - (to) Royal Society of London (1), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - S, 1956-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Schabert, Kyrill (4), 1956, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sellers, Mrs. Eleanor (4), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - (to) Smith, Lylle (with list of persons to whom copies sent) (4), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Stone, Robert B. (3), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Tart, Charles T. (4), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Taylor, Walter A. (16), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Tillich, Paul (3), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Toynbee, Arnold (2), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Turner, Malcolm (2), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - U.S. Naval Observatory (3), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - (to) Von Faber du Faur, Curt (3), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - W, 1956-1957, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Walter, W. Grey (with list of people to whom copies sent) (8), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Weiss, Paul (7), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - (to) Yang, Chen Ning (1), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Unidentified, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Instructions to executors of will, 1956, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Writings, Diary, Notes and Research Materials, 1935-1940, 1949-1968, undated; Series II; 3; (7 boxes)
  Material in this series is arranged alphabetically by type and then by title.
  - Addresses
    - "Article for Florida", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Don't Decorate", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "New Building Programs" (two versions), 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Some Problems in Spontaneous Experience", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles
    - "Architecture and Federal Union", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Art - Antidote to War", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Building Programs: Plan, Budget and Money" (written with E.S. Emerson), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "The Compulsion to Symbolize" (one copy apparently annotated by Jung), 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Design for a House of God" (together with plans and drawing), 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Extension of Extemporaneous Remarks on Fine Arts in the College Union Program", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "For Practice in Living", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Garble", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Hidden Variable", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "How is E.S.P. Limited", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Is Time Conserved" (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Multiplicity and Discreteness", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Notes - 1966" (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Notes on a Series of Postulates Leading to a Super-Physical Hypothesis of Extra-Sensory Perception", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Notes on a Theory of Perception and the Relation of Psychological to Physical Reality", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Notes on the Limitations to Psychic Knowledge", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "On the Death and Rebirth of Symbols", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Preparation of Wild Duck for the Table" (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "A Quantitative Approach to a Law of Psychokinesis", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "To Relate the Energy of Radiation to the Force of Gravity", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Telepathy and the Nature of Mystical Experience", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Theatre Architecture in Education", undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Thoughts on Reading McLuhan", 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Thoughts on Union Architecture", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "What Architecture Can We Afford", 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Untitled article sent to the Saturday Review, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Books
    - Microcosm and Macrocosm
      - Draft, original: title page - Chapter VI, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Draft, original: Chapter VII - Chapter IX, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Draft, original: Appendix I - X, Bibliography, Chapter XX, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Draft, publisher's: title page - Chapter VI, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Draft, publisher's: Chapter VII - Chapter IX, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Draft, publisher's: Appendix I - X, 1962-1963 undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Draft, [final?]: title page - Chapter VI, [1966?] (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Draft, [final?]: Chapter VII - Chapter XIII, [1966?] (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Draft, [final?]: Chapter XIV - Chapter XX, [1966?] (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Notes and research material: index to, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Notes and research material: folder A - "miscellaneous important calculations", 1954, 1960-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Notes and research material: folder B -"notes on Chapter IX 1961" (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Notes and research material: folder C - "nucleus", 1936, 1960, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Notes and research material: folder D - "miscellaneous discussions", 1960-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Notes and research material: folder E - "satellite genesis, calculations 1961" (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Notes and research material: folder F- "solar system", 1961, 1964-1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Notes and research material: folder G - "miscellaneous background publications", 1957-1958, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Published edition, annotated by Hare, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - The Multiple Universe
      - Draft, first: Chapter I - Chapter XIII, Appendix I, 1966 March (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Drafts: Chapter I - Chapter XI, 1967 March (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Draft: acknowledgements, Appendix 9, 1967 September (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Draft: title page - Appendix I, 1967 [Oct?] (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Draft: Appendix II - Bibliography, 1967 [Oct?] (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Draft: Appendix 9 [not used?], acknowledgements, note for dust jacket, notes to copy editor, layout for bibliography, 1967 [Oct?] (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Draft, [publisher's copy?): title page - Appendix 3, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Draft, [publisher's copy?]: Appendix 4 - Bibliography, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Index cards, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Note for jacket, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Proofs, galley, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Notes and research material: "Time notes for both Microcosm and Macrocosm and Multiple Universe ", 1962-1963, 1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Notes and research material, 1951, 1964-1966, undated (Box 5, Folder 43-46)
  - Diary, 1956-1959
    - Summary of pages 1 - 660, 1956-1959 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Pages 1 - 132, 1956 February - August 16 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Pages 133 - 257, 1956 August 17 - 1957 February 26 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Pages 258 - 390, 1957 February 27 - August 1 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Pages 391 - 518, 1957 August 2 - 1958 March 13 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Pages 519 - 690, 1958 March 14 - 1959 July 2 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Pages 691 - 850, 1959 July 3 - 1961 April 2 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Pages 851 - 985, 1961 April 3 - 1963 August 2 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Pages 986 - 1133, 1963 August 3 - 1966 July 17 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Pages 1134 - 1264, 1966 July 18 - 1968 August 29 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Notes and Research Materials
    - "Bio-physics", 1949, 1962, undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - "Blackett and Hypnosis", 1962, 1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - "Current design", 1956, 1960, 1963, 1966-1967, undated (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - "Current design" (cont'd), 1956, 1961, 1963-1967, undated (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - "Current work", 1965, 1967, undated (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - "Earlier E.S.P.", 1964-1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - "Earlier material 1956-1958", 1956-1957, 1958? (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - "E.S.P. [and?] the Hidden Variable", 1965,undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - "Forwald experiment", 1962, 1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - "Forwald experiment" (cont'd), 1962, undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - "General, old notes", 1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - "Magnetic [moment?] notes. Electron model notes", undated (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - "Mandala Vision", 1956 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - "Molecular Bond, Spring '63", 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - "Multiplicity and Descreteness notes", 1966 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - "Multiplicity and Descreteness notes" (cont'd), 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 71-73)
    - "Planet spacing Law notes", 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - "Taken in New Haven on [Dirac's?] article on the Ether", 1963? (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - "Uncertainty, Electron diffraction, Wave particle notes", 1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - "Venus notes", 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - untitled "Notes 56-59", 1956-1960, undated (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Article by Charon, Jean E. "On a Synthetic Theory for the Structure of Universe", undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - notes on the article by Hare, undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1961-1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Reprints of articles relating to the Lifwynn Foundation, 1940, 1950, 1961, 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Examination essay, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Theatrical sketch by Hare, Montgomery (brother): "Venus Shot", undated (Box 8, Folder 80)